# Rakesh Chowdary Machineni, M.S

in Rakesh Chowdary Machineni / ■ Rakesh C.Machineni@gmail.com / 📘 +1 734.968.9425 / • Austin, TX

#### SUMMARY

AI Researcher and Full-Stack Developer with 4+ years of experience in multimodal AI solutions, specializing in computer vision. Proven track record publications in top-tier conferences and deploying AI solutions across diverse industries, including automotive and retail.

### **EDUCATION**

**Masters in Electrical and Computer Engineering (Computer Vision Specialization)** 

2021 - 2023

University of Michigan (GPA of 4.0/4.0)

Ann Arbor, Michigan

• Research primarily focused on developing novel Video, Point Cloud & Image Compression Models

#### **Bachelor of Technology in Electrical Engineering**

2015 - 2019

Indian Institute of Technology Tirupati (CGPA of 8.90/10.0)

Tirupati, India

• Hands on experience with C/C++, Python, OpenCV, ROS Raspberry Pi, Arduino, Autonomous Bot Perception

#### **EXPERIENCE**

• Research Scientist – Computer Vision | Rockwell Automation | Austin, TX

July 2023 - Present

- Designed **LenzAI**, a Closed-Loop Machine Vision AI solution that accommodates Data Labeling, Model Training, Performance Monitoring, and Analytics (tables, graph visualization over time) for seamless integration by industrial operators
- Advanced AI-driven data labeling platform utilizing Instance Segmentation and Monocular Depth Estimation, reducing per-image annotation time by 10X; integrated Active Learning with Model-Health Monitoring to minimize redundant labeling, reducing total required training samples by 30%
- Developed a novel zone transformation and unsupervised depth-based wrinkle detection system for automotive seat inspection, former dynamically adapts to geometric displacements of seats eliminating manual recalibration of ironing bot, latter achieved an 83% precision and 97% recall value in wrinkle identification on BMW seats while providing heatmaps showcasing the wrinkle severity
- Implemented video-processing **AI** for CPU/GPU to model periodic patterns, enabling real-time closed-loop control systems for dynamic state classification and actuation
- Filed a **patent** on the video analytics technology and co-authored a **technical paper** with BMW, featuring the success of AI in seat quality control; a second joint patent is pending.
- Architected scalable deployment using **Docker** and **Portainer**, achieving **99.99%** uptime while supporting **100**+ concurrent inference requests; successfully implemented across **3**+ paying customers, processing over **100,000** images monthly
- Engineered seamless integration with **PLCs** (e.g., Rockwell, Siemens) and industrial **cameras** (e.g., Cognex, Keyence, GenICam), achieving sub-**50ms** latency in real-time applications
- Tools: Django, React, RTKQuery, OpenCV, PyTorch, Spark MLLib, ONNX, PostgreSQL

#### • Graduate Research Assistant | University of Michigan | Ann Arbor, MI

2021 - 2023

- Proposed Multi-Mode Video Compression (MMVC) framework with block-based prediction mode selection and adaptive entropy coding, CVPR 2023
- Outperformed **SOTA** learning-based and conventional codecs on popular benchmark datasets in PSNR & MS-SSIM metrics, specifically a **1dB** PSNR and **0.02** MS-SSIM improvement at a very low, **0.1** bit-rate
- Tools: Qualitative and Quantitative Studies, PyTorch, RAFT, Arithmetic Coding, Quantization, ConvLSTM

- Designed an Item Recognition software for **No Touch Checkout**, enabling automated billing in grocery stores
- Deployed solution achieved a 98% classification accuracy in real-time speed
- Tools: Keras, Tensorflow, fine-tuned CNN's, Jupyter, Classical Computer Vision methods, PyQt
- Undergraduate Research Assistant | VISA Lab | Tirupati, India

2018 - 2019

- A novel end-to-end deep learning model to profile the 3D shape of objects from deformed fringe patterns,
  CVIU 2020
- Reconstructed shapes at -5dB SNR with a 0.005 RMSE surpassing traditional approaches by 10 folds

## **PUBLICATIONS**

- Bowen Liu, **Rakesh Chowdary Machineni**, Yu Chen, Shiyu Liu, Hun Seok Kim "MMVC: Learned Multi-Mode Video Compression with Block-based Prediction Mode Selection and Density-Adaptive Entropy Coding." in The IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), 2023.
- Rakesh Chowdary Machineni, G. E. Spoorthi, Krishna Sumanth V, Subrahmanyam G, Rama Krishna S. S. G "End-to-end deep learning-based fringe projection framework for 3D profiling of objects." Comput. Vis. Image Underst. 199: 103023 (2020).

# OTHER PROJECTS

- **Stock Predictor:** Built an IR system using query expansion and DistilBERT to predict relevance of text to stock price movements, achieving **0.8593** MSE. (link)
- Vision Transformer & SiamRPN++: Finetuned ViT for 99.5% CIFAR-10 and 84.65% Tiny ImageNet accuracy; implemented SiamRPN++ tracker with 51% EAO. (link)
- **NLP Models:** Developed RNN, LSTM, and attention-based captioning models scoring up to **18.1** BLEU on COCO; built transformer for arithmetic operations. (<a href="link"><u>link</u></a>)
- Image Generation & Style Transfer: Implemented GAN variants to generate MNIST-like digits; performed artistic style transfer using content, style, and TV losses. (link)
- Annotation Tool & Grad-CAM: Designed polygon annotation tool; conducted Grad-CAM analysis on ImageNet-trained ResNet50. (link)
- Object Detection: Achieved 43.63%, 35.28%, 40.51% mAP on VOC with FCOS, YOLO, and Faster R-CNN; built simple CLIP-like model for image-text retrieval and ImageNet classification. (link)
- **Depth, Panorama, Navigation:** Implemented stereo rectification, ORB/RANSAC panorama stitching, and depth estimation for autonomous systems.